Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, today's דף Daf is, hope
that's officially ס״ז, Samech Zayin, we are picking up
towards the bottom of the גמרא Gemara in ס״ו עמוד א׳, Samech
Vav Amud Aleph, so let's see how close we can get to
getting to what today's דף Daf actually officially is. The issue in
the משנה Mishnah is what happens in terms of the slaves of
a woman who is married to a כהן, Kohen, that they're two
types: the נכסי מלוג, Nichsei Milug, the slave that she retains title
to which is totally hers except he gets the right of usage,
and the slaves that he owns, the נכסי צאן ברזל. Nichsei Tzon
Barzel. And the משנה Mishnah deals with the ones that she owns,
those are the more interesting ones, and if she's an אלמנה Almanah
or גרושה, Gerushah, חלוצה, Chalutzah, or אלמנה לכהן גדול, Almanah l'Kohen Gadol,
she becomes a חללה Chalalah in the mix, so then the point
is she can't eat תרומה Terumah by virtue of being married to
her—him. What about her slaves? Are they eating through her, and then
they cannot eat תרומה? Terumah? That's what the משנה Mishnah says. The
משנה Mishnah says they cannot eat תרומה, Terumah, or maybe we should
say essentially no, this is all back connected to the כהן Kohen
and therefore the slaves can. So the משנה Mishnah says that they
cannot, and the גמרא Gemara says that the reason is because
קנינו שקנה קנין, Kinyano she-kanah kinyan, that is the phrase referring to
the wife of a קנין, Kinyan, something that is obviously challenging that
we'll have to deal with when we get to מסכת קידושין, Masechet
Kiddushin, and therefore, this is his קנין, Kinyan, his wife that owns
something, these slaves and they eat תרומה, Terumah, and why—so that sounds
like it's about him. And the גמרא Gemara says yeah, but if
she can't eat, if she's not אוכל Ochel she's not מאכיל, Maachil,
ultimately they're eating through her. And now the גמרא Gemara is questioning
whether that is actually the principle. Does—do—are they entitled to eat through
her, or does it connect back to him? So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: והרי ממזר שאין אוכל, Va-harei mamzer she-ein ochel,
the line starts with the word שאין אוכל she-ein ochel of the
word ממזר, Mamzer, the last word of the line right near the
תוספות Tosafot that starts with the word אלא. Ella. והרי ממזר שאין
אוכל ומאכיל. Va-harei mamzer she-ein ochel u-maachil. How about a ממזר Mamzer
who can't eat but he can allow his mother to eat? What's
the case here? The case here is not really about a ממזר,
Mamzer, it's ממזר Mamzer just to make this more drastic, but the
case here is that you've got basically a כהן Kohen who is
married to a woman, okay, and they have a daughter, okay, and
this daughter let's even do it in a—is married to a ממזר.
Mamzer. Now really it doesn't have to be a ממזר. Mamzer. It
could just be a ישראל, Yisrael, okay, but it's an extreme giving
an example,
and they have a child, right? Now, is this child a
כהן?
Kohen? No, right?
Because his mother was the daughter of a כהן, Kohen, but his
father's a ישראל Yisrael or even a ממזר Mamzer if the case
would be a ממזר. Mamzer. He's not a כהן. Kohen. Can his
mother now—this כהן Kohen dies or they get divorced or whatever. Can
his mother—let's say they—I'm sorry, let's say the כהן Kohen dies, okay?
Can the mother—not divorce—the כהן Kohen dies, okay, can the mother eat
תרומה? Terumah? Does anybody know the הלכה Halacha that if a woman
is married to a כהן Kohen and the כהן Kohen dies whether
the woman can continue eating תרומה? Terumah?
She can get her כתובה Ketubah so
then—no no no, no גט. get. The כהן Kohen dies. No.
I mean—no, no, no, no גט. get. The כהן Kohen dies.
Forget the כתובה. Ketubah. Can a woman who is married to a
כהן Kohen and the כהן Kohen dies continue eating תרומה? Terumah? Unless
she has a child—not a son, a child—from the כהן, Kohen, then
she's still connected to the כהן's Kohen family and then she can
eat תרומה. Terumah. Now the הלכה Halacha is even if it's a
grandchild, okay? So in this case the כהן Kohen dies, let's say
her daughter dies, she can still eat תרומה Terumah because she has
a grandchild that is ultimately from the כהן's Kohen family, even though
it comes through a daughter and therefore the child is not a
כהן, Kohen, the child could even be a ממזר, Mamzer, okay? But
because she's got a grandchild that came through her marriage to the
כהן, Kohen, she can still eat תרומה. Terumah. So the גמרא Gemara
says forever as long as the child's alive. Even though the daughter
and child—even though the child—not the daughter—until she was married whatever could—so
that's why it's even more radical to here because, you know, this
grandchild would never be able to eat תרומה, Terumah, right? The daughter
could before she got married, okay, but this grandchild would never be
able to eat תרומה Terumah and nevertheless her grandmother can eat on
her behalf.
You see, like the rest of her life after—even after she got
her כתובה Ketubah paid. Yep.
Yep. So, okay, so thank you. So, okay, so therefore we say,
so you see that somebody can have somebody eat on their behalf
even if they themselves cannot eat. So the גמרא Gemara says—so all
those were in the words והרי ממזר שאין אוכל ומאכיל. Va-harei mamzer
she-ein ochel u-maachil.
So this grandchild doesn't eat, even a ממזר, Mamzer, and could make
her grandmother eat. אמר רבינא קנין אוכל קאמר. Amar Ravina kinyan ochel
ka'amar.
No no no, obviously there are cases where a descendant can eat—can—a
descendant won't eat and the grandmother will or the mother will, okay?
That's because that's based on the idea that because it's a child
or a descendant, it's back ultimately connects her to the family of
the כהן. Kohen. That's a different
category, we're not... This is a different story. This is eating by
virtue of a child or a grandchild. That's not relevant. We're talking
about eating by virtue of being owned. Okay, and that's our issue.
קנין אוכל, kinyan ochel, we're talking about, okay, קמן. kaman. קנין אוכל
מאכיל. kinyan ochel ma'achil. Only a קנין kinyan that eats can feed,
okay? קנין שאינו אוכל אינו מאכיל. kinyan she'eino ochel eino ma'achil. So
back to the principle that again, calling the wife a קנין, kinyan,
and if she can't eat, then she can't have her slaves eat,
because ultimately they're eating through her. That's explanation number one of the
משנה. Mishnah. Now we get to explanation number two. ורבא אמר מדאורייתא
מאכלי. VeRava amar mide'oraisa me'achlei. You know what? You're right. The slaves
of the wife really could eat because indirectly they're connected to the
כהן, Kohen, and forget the fact that the wife can't eat. In
principle, they can. מדאורייתא מאכלי. mide'oraisa me'achlei. ורבנן הוא דגזרו בהו. Verabbanan
hu degazru behu.
The Rabbis didn't let the slaves eat in this case, כדי שתאמר,
kedei shetomar, and this was, they did this as an incentive to
try to get them divorced, because you know, the כהן'ס Kohen's married
to a גרושה, gerusha, חלוצה, chalutza, or כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to
an אלמנה. almanah. We don't like that situation. So we want to
try to create certain pressures in order to get them divorced. And
here's what we're going to say. She'll say, look, אני איני אוכלת.
ani eini ochelet. Here he is, my כהן Kohen has all this
תרומה, terumah, it's a major source of his income let's say. I
can't eat from it, I'm a חללה. chalalah. עבדי אינם אוכלים. avadai
einam ochlim. My slaves can't even, I can't even pass on that
תרומה terumah to my slaves, okay? Therefore, זונה היא אצלו. zonah hi
etzlo. I'm basically like a prostitute to him. Okay, I'm not even
really married to him. I don't get תרומה, terumah, my slaves don't
get תרומה. terumah. And therefore, זונה היא אצלו, zonah hi etzlo, where
am I? ואתי לאפוקה, va'ati lefuka,
and maybe therefore he'll divorce her. That'll cause that sense of discontent
and that'll lead to divorce. So רבא Rava says in principle you're
right, the slaves could eat because they're not even through her, they're
eating because they're connected to him, but it's a way of our
disapproval of the whole situation. Okay, that's רבא'ס Rava's answer. רב אשי
אמר גזרה שמא תאכילהו אחר מיתה. Rav Ashi amar gezerah shema ta'achilah
achar misah. רב אשי Rav Ashi agreed, in principle the slaves could
eat, but here's the reason why not. גזרה שמא תאכילהו אחר מיתה.
gezerah shema ta'achilah achar misah.
We're afraid that she will feed her slaves this תרומה terumah even
after the כהן Kohen dies. She's only eating by virtue of the
כהן. Kohen. If we let her feed the תרומה terumah now, she'll
continue to feed them after the כהן Kohen dies. Of course the
גמרא Gemara says that should be a concern all the time. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מעתה בת ישראל שניסת לכהן, ela me'ata
bas Yisrael shenises leKohen, the classic case of a Jewish woman married
to a כהן, Kohen, לא תאכיל, lo ta'achil, let her not feed
her slaves תרומה. terumah. גזרה שמא תאכיל אחר מיתה. gezerah shema ta'achil
achar misah. Maybe she'll continue to feed them after death. אלא אמר
רב אשי, ela amar Rav Ashi, so רב אשי Rav Ashi says
fine, forget that. באלמנה כהנת. bealmanah Kohenes.
Here's the reason why we don't allow this case, because there's one
case we do have to be concerned about that will lead to
a problem. What's the case? That the woman who's married to the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the אלמנה, almanah, okay, she actually is also
a בת כהן. bas Kohen. Now, if she's a בת כהן, bas
Kohen, she will say the following, דאתיא למימר. de'asya leru'ei. She'll come
to sort of פסקן pasken for herself. And here's what she'll come
to reason.
מעיקרא אכלי בתרומה דבי נשא. me'ikara achli bisrumah debei nasha. Originally these
slaves were eating תרומה terumah because of דבי נשא, debei nasha, my
mother's house, but meaning you know, the house that I came from.
You know, actually it means the father's house, but not my husband,
not who I'm married to. So I was eating תרומה, terumah, they
were eating תרומה terumah by virtue of the fact that I was
a בת כהן. bas Kohen. Where
were we? Or actually, no, she's, yeah, okay, sorry. דבי נשא. debei
nasha. באלמנה כהנת דאתיא למימר. bealmanah Kohenes de'asya leru'ei. מעיקרא אכלי בתרומה
דבי נשא. me'ikara achli bisrumah debei nasha.
Hold on, let me just check רש״י Rashi one second.
Yeah.
Okay. Originally they ate תרומה terumah when I was, you know, in
my father's house. Okay, these slaves, because they were eating by virtue
of the fact that I was a בת כהן. bas Kohen. אינסיבה
להאי כהן, inseiva lehah Kohen, I married this
כהן. Kohen. אכלי בתרומה דגבראי, achli bisrumah degavrai,
they continued to eat תרומה terumah by virtue of my husband. והשתא
הדרי לה מילתא כמעיקרא. vehashta hadri leh milsa kemaiseh. Now that my
husband has died, they'll go back to their original state and they'll
continue to eat תרומה. terumah. דלא ידעה, delo yade'a, she's not aware,
דמעיקרא לא שויתא לנפשה חללה. deme'ikara lo shavisah linafshah chalalah.
Before when they were eating when before she got married to this
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, then the slaves were eating because she wasn't
yet a חללה. chalalah. השתא שויתא נפשה חללה. hashta shavisah nafshah chalalah.
Now she's become a חללה, chalalah, so they can't eat. Okay, so
basically what he's saying is complicated, but basically you're right, in principle
these slaves can eat because they're connected to the כהן, Kohen, but
we're afraid she'll continue to have them eat after she gets divorced,
in, after the כהן Kohen dies. Isn't that a concern all the
time? No, here there'll be a particular logic she'll think. She'll think,
look, my slaves were eating before I married the כהן Kohen because
I'm a
בת... bas... But she won't be aware that in the process she
became a חללה chalala and that's because she's an אלמנה almana married
to a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and that makes her into a
חללה chalala when they have sex with a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
That's the whole assumption of the משנה. Mishna. The problem of the
משנה, Mishna, the reason she becomes disqualified is that it's a forbidden
marriage between a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and an אלמנה almana or
a כהן Kohen and a גרושה grusha and that makes her a
חללה. chalala. That's the major principle of what makes this case an
interesting case, is that she's the חללה. chalala. So because in the
process she became a חללה, chalala, even after the כהן Kohen dies,
she does not go back to having her slaves eat because then
as a חללה chalala her slaves can no longer eat.
Yes, the word כהנת kohenes means the daughter of a כהן?
Kohen? Yes. So if she became a חללה, chalala, Michael was going
to say, yes.
So in the case on the right where that in the black?
So they don't marry to a כהן. Kohen.
Right, no, which is a regular person. In contrast to this case,
because she's a חללה, chalala, she can't have her slaves eat. This
woman would be able to even have her slaves eat if she
had a kid, right?
Yes. All right, yes, Dov, you had a question?
Just want to clarify. She was already an אלמנה almana when she
married the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. She didn't become an אלמנה almana
by virtue of his death.
No, but she became a חללה chalala because she was an אלמנה
almana and had sex with a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
That made her a חללה. chalala. What about for the אלמנה almana
of a כהן Kohen herself? She herself?
She can eat as long as there's a child.
Right. But not here because she's a חללה. chalala.
All right, חברא, chevra, moving on. It's another reason, a complicated reason
why in principle these slaves could eat, but because it'll lead to
a problem where she'll continue to feed them where she won't be
allowed to. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תינח אלמנה כהנת,
teinach almana kohenes, אלמנה... almana...
so that makes sense in a case of אלמנה כהנת, almana kohenes,
but אלמנה בת ישראל, almana bas yisrael, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika
lemeimar?
Why does this משנה Mishna apply even to a case of a
non-כהנת? kohenes?
So the גמרא Gemara says: במנוסה לא פליגי רבנן, be'manusa lo pligi
rabbanan, או לא פלוג. o lo plug. Since there's one case they're
concerned about that she might say we'll go back to square one
and so on, therefore they say in all these cases the slaves
can't eat. So basically we have two answers. One is that the
slaves only eat by virtue of her, which is the simple answer,
and she's a חללה chalala and they can't eat. The other is
that they eat by virtue of him, and there are special reasons
that we have to make a גזירה gezeira here. Moving on. איתמר.
itmar. המכנסת שום לבעלה. hamachneses shum le'ba'ala.
A woman who brings in garlic to her husband. No, I'm teasing.
A woman, שום shum means that you evaluate the property,
and שמין shamin means like to assess the property, that's the word,
you assess the property. And that's what we refer to as the
נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. That's when the כתובה kesuba says,
בין בתכשיטי בין בזהב בין בכסף בין בזהב הכל קיבל עליו החתן
במאה זקוקים כסף צרוף, bein betachshitei bein be'zahav bein be'chesef bein be'zahav
hakol kibel alav hachassan be'meiah zkukim kesef tzoruf,
which means here's all the property she's bringing in, we're assessing their
value to be a hundred coins of silver. And therefore when they
get divorced, if they get divorced or if he dies first, she's
able to take out of the marriage, out of the husband's estate,
these
hundred silver coins because or whatever the זקוק zkuk is, anyway, ten
thousand dollars. Now, so that means you assess their value and that's
the amount the husband owns. That's נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel.
Title transfers to the husband. נכסי מלוג nichsei melog she retains title,
he just gets use. Here title transfers, the title is transferring and
then he's going to be the one that's going to benefit from
the increase but also suffer any loss. So what she gets is
the dollar value. She's assured the dollar value. And that's why you
do a שומא, shuma, you do an assessment of how much it's
worth. So מכנסת שום לבעלה. machneses shum le'ba'ala. She brings in money
into the marriage, it's נכסי צאן ברזל, nichsei tzon barzel, you do
an assessment, you determine how much it's worth. Now, this is the
question that I think Michael or somebody asked the other day. Let's
say the husband dies and the stuff is still around, the field
is still around, the car, the slaves, whatever it is, is still
around. She wants to take the stuff back. She doesn't just want
the dollar value. So what's the story? היא אומרת כלי אני נוטלת,
hi omeres keilai ani noseles, I'm taking back my vessels. הוא אומר,
hu omer, he says, so we're dealing in a case of divorce,
הוא אומר דמים אני נותן. hu omer damim ani nosen. No, I'm
only paying you for them. I totally took possession, hundred percent mine,
and I just owe you money. So that's the question. Is it
fundamentally that she still has a right to reclaim them? Or it's
just that any benefit he'll keep, any loss he'll have to suffer,
but fundamentally they began as hers and she has a right to
reclaim them? Or it's fundamentally he just owes her money. So הדין
עם מי? hadin im mi? Who's right? Who has law on their
side? רב יהודה אמר רב יהודה, rav yehuda amar rav yehuda, Rav
Yehuda said, הדין עמה. hadin immah. She's got the law on her
side. She's able to claim back her vessels. רב אמי אמר הדין
עמו, rav ami amar hadin immo, the law is with him. רב
יהודה אמר הדין עמה משום שבח בית אביה. rav yehuda amar hadin
immah mishum shevach beis aviha. It
is her because it's the benefit of the father's house, the increase
of the father's house, meaning this is the stuff that she got
for dowry from her father's house and therefore she's entitled to it,
which is a pretty funny argument. like a legal point, it's just
somehow saying she should be entitled to it. This is what she
got from her father's dowry, she should be entitled to reclaim it.
רב אמי אמר הדין
עמו. Rav Ami Amar Hadin Imo. כי בא אפרפתא Kiva Aprufda that
he's entitled to it. כיון דאמר מר, Keivan De’amar Mar, since we
say, אם מתו מתו לו ואם הוקירו הוקירו לו, Im mesu mesu
lo ve’im hokiru hokiru lo, if they die—like that's in the mishna,
like it describes the consequence of נכסי צאן ברזל—if nichsei tzon barzel
they die, it's his loss, if they increase, it's his gain.
So what does that show you? So now here, it's not in
my Gemara, but most of these Gemaras have actually what they what
they all the all the manuscripts, there was, yeah, here it is,
in all the manuscripts there's actually a line that's not in our
Gemara and you could see how it got left out because it's
considered השמטה על ידי הדומות hashmata al yedei hadomos when the Sofer
jumps from one line to the next because it's the same word.
So here's actually how the sentence ends. It says, so since it
says if they die it's his loss and if they increase it's
his increase, so ברשותיה קיימי. birshusei kayami. So clearly it shows that
it's now in his possession. וכדידיה דמו, U’ch’didei damu, it's like it's
fully his. And that's the proof, right? That's pretty reasonable. If it
increases it's his, if it decreases he loses, it shows it's his
proof. So then the Gemara now says, תנן, Tnan, let's look at
our mishna. ואלו הן נכסי צאן ברזל אם מתו מתו לו ואם
הוקירו הוקירו לו. Ve’elu hein nichsei tzon barzel im mesu mesu lo
ve’im hokiru hokiru lo. So it goes back and quotes the same
line. Okay, so basically he says since if it increases or decreases
it's all his, obviously that shows that it's come to his possession.
Now let's take a look at what we can prove from the
mishna. Okay, so it says הוקירו לו הואיל וחייב באחריותן יאכלו. hokiru
lo ho’il ve’chayav b’achrayusan yochlu.
So it says and that's supposed to be a proof. It says
he's obligated in their, you know, he's responsible for them and therefore
they eat. So that seems to prove two things. Number one, it
says he's responsible for them. That seems to signal that they're his.
And number two, if they can eat—if these slaves that he got
as נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei tzon barzel from the dowry can eat
even though his wife is a חללה—that challalah shows that they're considered
to be his slaves, right? So the simple sense of the mishna
clearly is that these are his slaves and that's why they're entitled
to eat. So doesn't that prove that she cannot retrieve them if
there's a divorce? So אמר רב ספרא, Amar Rav Safra, so Rav
Safra says back, no, מי קתני והן שלו? mi katani vehen shelo?
It doesn't say the slaves are his. Look, the language is very
specific. It says הואיל וחייב באחריותן קתני. ho’il ve’chayav b’achrayusan katani.
It says that he's responsible for them. So it's a legal sort
of relationship to them where yes, he benefits from any increase, he
suffers any loss, but that doesn't have to mean that they're considered
his, right? That could just be the condition of the, you know,
the nature of the sort of legal rights that he has and
responsibilities without absolutely claiming that they're his. The language is חייב באחריותן.
chayav b’achrayusan. The language is not that they're his. ולעולם לאו דידיה
נינהו, U’le’olam lav didei ninhu, they're not his. Okay, but now you
have an interesting situation that they're not his, but they still eat
תרומה terumah by virtue of this relationship, right? So now we get
always into this interesting gray zone, right? Is it possible that they're
eating תרומה terumah because of he is so much sort of has
so many rights about regarding them that they're eating and responsibilities that
they're eating תרומה terumah because it's as if they're his, but still
being able to technically say they're still not his, they're still hers,
and she can still retrieve them? So let's take a look. That's
the debate. So the Gemara says like this,
וכל היכא דחייב באחריותן אכלי בתרומה? v’chol heicha de’chayav b’achrayusan achli b’terumah?
So that's what the Gemara is going to question. So are you
really going to tell me that being responsible
for their loss is enough of a relationship to entitle them to
eat תרומה terumah even if they're not his? Let's test that theory
because now you're saying you don't have to own them and they
can still eat
תרומה. terumah. דהתנן, Dehatnan, we taught in the mishna, ישראל ששכר פרה
מכהן, Yisrael she’sachar parah m’kohen, a Yisrael rented a cow from a
kohen. Now when you rent a cow, you're liable for loss and
theft. That's a type of a חיוב אחריות, chiyuv achrayus, you're liable
for any loss. הרי זה יאכילנה כרשיני תרומה. Harei zeh ya’achilennah karshinei
terumah. Since they're still owned by a kohen, they're considered the kohen's
and he can feed the cow this, like, you know, whatever, animal
fodder of תרומה. terumah. In the reverse, כהן ששכר פרה מישראל, kohen
she’sachar parah mi’Yisrael, if a kohen rented a cow from Yisrael, אף
על פי שמזונותיה עליו, af al pi shemezonoseha alav, even though he
is responsible to feed the cow, okay, so he's responsible to feed
the cow, he'll be responsible for any loss, nevertheless, even though he's
got all this responsibility and חיוב אחריות, chiyuv achrayus, they're still the
Yisrael's cow. And the halacha is לא יאכילנה כרשיני תרומה, lo ya’achilennah
karshinei terumah, he can't feed it תרומה. terumah. So you see being
חייב באחריות chayav b’achrayus is not enough to
allow something you don't own to eat תרומה. terumah. So if the
slaves are eating תרומה, terumah, it must be more than he's just
responsible for them, it must be a real sense of ownership. So
the Gemara says one minute, there are different degrees of what it
means to be responsible for something. It's a sliding scale. Renting is
a low level of responsibility. The relationship he has to the slaves
is a high level of responsibility. That makes things different. So the
Gemara says one minute. ופירכא? U’fircha? Does that make sense that that's
a proof against... this idea? ניהי נמי דחייב בגניבה ואבידה Nihei nami
dechayeiv bigniva ve'aveida when you rent it's true you're liable for theft
and loss, but for אונס, onnes, but here's a whole list of
things you're not liable for. Number two, if some some accident happens
to us, like the strike, you know, something's out of your control.
Number two, בכחישא, bikhishah, let's say it got thinner. You rent a
cow and it got thinner, you know, just naturally. You don't have
to somehow make up the difference unless you're actually negligent, right? Or,
you know, or somehow got weaker. Or בנפחא, binfacha,
let's say the market changed. You rented a cow, it was worth
a thousand dollars. You returned it, it was worth nine hundred because
the market changed. You got to give the guy a hundred dollars?
Of course not, right? So therefore your responsibility as a שוכר, socher,
a renter, is very limited for theft and loss, whereas when you
take the slaves in in the marriage, let's say the market changes.
You took the slaves in and the slaves were worth a thousand
dollars, and now when you're getting divorced and the slaves are worth
five hundred. They didn't get any worse, just the market changed. You
have to give your wife an extra five hundred dollars.
And even if you give the original slaves, you'd have to make
up the difference.
So that's a proof that it's not just some liability, it's really
a sense of ownership, because you always have to pay back the
full value. So it's nothing like normal liability. And therefore, and therefore,
says the גמרא, Gemara, we don't have to call it ownership. You're
right, it's starting to sound a lot like ownership. You've taken these
slaves, you get divorced a day later, and now because the market
has changed they're worth less, and you have to pay back more,
you have to give them back plus a hundred dollars. Okay, so
it doesn't sound like normal liability. It sounds like ownership with a
debt. But the גמרא Gemara is saying maybe not. We're going to
insist that there's this middle zone that's called she still owns it,
but you have complete liability. And also you get any complete any
increase in value. So you have all the consequences of ownership, but
we're not going to call it ownership. Okay, yes.
One thing I've put said in the Torah that unless the owner
came with the cow when you rented it, that you are respon...
No, that's when you borrow it, not when you rent it. Oh,
okay.
And the other thing is just this, the value that she gets
back, is it the value at the end of the period or
the value when it was original?
No, the value when he took it into the, when it was
originally assessed, yeah.
But what if it increased in value?
Then he gets to keep the difference. So that's the point. The
point is that this looks like ownership because all of the issues,
right, well, right, it's like, you know, so any... she gets the
money, she's entitled to get the full value back, but also any
increase, he keeps any increase, he makes up any difference. It doesn't
matter if he's at fault, not at fault, it's because market change,
whatever the reason is. So that looks a lot like, like he
took over title and she just is owed money. But the גמרא
Gemara is saying maybe we can insist not. Maybe we can insist
that she retains title, but he has a very unique set of
rights and responsibilities to this property that she has title to. Number
one is he's entitled to any increase in value. Number two is
he's obligated to pay up any loss in value, no matter how
much it's his fault or not his fault, or how much it's
about market changes. But maybe technically she still owns it. And therefore
this degree of חייב באחריותו, chayav beachrayuso, the slaves would eat תרומה.
terumah. Okay? So that's the argument. We all agree that it looks
a lot like ownership, but is it really ownership? We're saying it
might be that it's not ownership, but because it's this amount of
rights and responsibilities, therefore it's close enough that the slaves can eat
תרומה. terumah. All right?
Yes, so do these slaves have children? Who gets them?
She does or he does? He does.
Yeah. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara would say like this.
Okay. הלו דמיא אלא לסיפא. Halo damya ela leseifa. So if you
want to compare it to a case, it's compared to a of
a high level of rights and responsibilities. It's comparable to the end
of this ברייתא, braita, which is what? הלו דמיא, Halo damya, where
am I? אלא לסיפא, ישראל ששם פרה מכהן. Ela leseifa, Yisrael shesham
para miKohen.
If a ישראל Yisrael basically assesses the cost of a cow from
a כהן, Kohen, and he takes it, and he says I will
give you back its full value, then לא יאכילנה כשיני תרומה. lo
ya'achilenah kashini terumah. He can't feed it תרומה terumah because then it
becomes like his, even though it doesn't say he clearly took title.
He just assessed the value and promises to restore it in full
value, regardless of fault or anything. אבל כהן ששם פרה מישראל, Aval
Kohen shesham para miYisrael, but if a כהן Kohen assesses the cow
from a ישראל Yisrael and promises to return it in full value
regardless of market or any other changes, then יכילנה כשיני תרומה. yachilenah
kashini terumah. He can feed it, even though that's not actually taking
title. So of course you could say no, maybe you could argue
back and say no that is taking title. But this is the
question, this unique relationship that he has to restore it in full
value and he gets any benefit and any increase, do we say
okay effectively that's ownership, or do we say no it exists in
some space where she still owns it but he has all those
rights? Okay? But maybe that's enough that they'll eat תרומה, terumah, but
technically therefore she's still entitled to demand taking it back. Okay, so
let's take a look. יתיב רבה ורב יוסף, Yasiv Rava veRav Yosef,
so Rava and Rav Yosef were sitting בשילהי פירקא דרב נחמן, beshila
pirka deRav Nachman, at the end of the דרשה drasha of רב
נחמן. Rav Nachman. Okay, but maybe that's enough that they'll eat תרומה,
trumah, but technically therefore she's still entitled to the man taking it
back. Okay, so let's take a look. יתיב רבא ורב יוסף, Yasiv
Rava v'Rav Yosef, so רבא Rava and רב יוסף Rav Yosef were
sitting בשלהי פרקי דרב נחמן b'shili pirkei d'Rav Nachman at the end
of the דרשה drasha of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. So רב נחמן
Rav Nachman finished his דרשה drasha and they were hanging back and
talking in תורה. Torah. ויתבי ואמרי V'yasvi v'amri and they were sitting
and saying, תניא כוותיה דרב יהודה ותניא כוותיה דרבי אמי. Tanya k'vassa
d'Rav Yehuda v'tanya k'vassa d'Rabbi Ami. We taught like רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda that she's entitled to it, and we taught like רבי אמי
Rabbi Ami that he's entitled to it. תניא כוותיה דרבי אמי. Tanya
k'vassa d'Rabbi Ami. We taught like רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. עבדי צאן
ברזל יוצאין בשן ועין לאיש, Avdei tzon barzel yotzin b'shen v'ayin l'ish,
אבל לא לאשה. aval lo l'isha.
Let's say these slaves that he took in, you know, as the
dowry and צאן ברזל, tzon barzel, he owes their value. He knocks
out their an eye or a two, then they would go out
because he's considered their master and they go out for free. But
if she knocks out an eye or a two, they don't go
out because she's not considered their master. So that sounds like he's
the one that has full title. Okay now, of course that's the
prima facie like רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. תניא כוותיה דרב יהודה. Tanya
k'vassa d'Rav Yehuda. We taught like רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. המכניסת שום
לבעלה, Hamachneses shum l'ba'alah,
so if she brings in this assessed valued property to her husband,
אם רצה בעל למכור לא ימכור. im ratza ba'al limkor lo yimkor.
He's not allowed to sell it. Right. Now the fact that he's
not allowed to sell it, why wouldn't he be allowed to sell
it? According to the idea that it's his, he could totally sell
it. He just has a debt to her. They're 100 percent his.
So the fact that he's not allowed showed that she's still entitled
to take it back out and that she still has rights to
it. מכרו שניהם
לפרנסה, Machru shneihem l'parnasa, now either of them sold it because they
needed, I don't know, you know, to put food on the table.
רש"י Rashi just says that's just a standard example. Did I skip
a line?
ולא עוד אלא אפילו הכניס לה שום
משלו.
V'lo od ela afilu hichnis lah
shum mishelo. Yeah.
No
I didn't. ולא עוד אלא אפילו הכניס לה שום משלו, V'lo od
ela afilu hichnis lah shum mishelo,
even if he basically contributed to her dowry, which is an interesting
idea. He said, 'Look here, take this lovely, you know, I don't
know, you know, my grandmother's china. That'll be part of your dowry
and I, you know, and I'll pay,' so essentially he's contributing to
her dowry and then she's going to take it out of the
marriage, or at least their value. Even in that case, אם רצה
בעל למכור לא ימכור. im ratza ba'al limkor lo yimkor. He can't
sell it because, which again shows that he doesn't really have full
title. Some degree she still has rights. מכרו שניהם לפרנסה, Machru shneihem
l'parnasa, if they both, if either of them as רש"י Rashi sells
it because they had to put food on the table. רש"י Rashi
says it doesn't have to be that reason, but that would just
be, otherwise you normally wouldn't sell. זה היה מעשה לפני רבן גמליאל,
Ze haya ma'aseh lifnei Rabban Gamliel, this came before רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel. ואמר הבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות, v'amar haba'al motzi miyad halakuchos, that
the sale is completely void and the husband retrieves it from the
people he sold it to because he has no rights to sell
the property that the wife brought in. Okay, so this seems like
a very good proof. If he really has full title and it's
just a debt, why would he not have rights to sell this
property? Okay, so that really seems like quite a good proof.
If he literally brought it in.
Well, yes, but property that he contributed, right. Okay. אמר רבא אמר
רב נחמן הלכה כרב יהודה. Amar Rava amar Rav Nachman halacha k'Rav
Yehuda.
So that last ברייתא braita was pretty persuasive. So now רבא Rava
is saying we rule like רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. She is entitled
to retrieve the property that she brought in. Again, if it's worth
more, here's an interesting question. If it's worth less, he makes up
the difference. If it's worth more, what does she do? So if
she brought in like, I don't know, 12 place settings of china
and now they've doubled in value, does she take out six or
does she take out 12 and pay back the difference? If she
brought in a vintage, I don't know, you know, Mustang, whatever, and
now it's doubled in value, you don't take away half a car.
So what do you do? Do you take the whole car and
pay the difference? That's not exactly clear how that will play out.
The גמרא Gemara will do like one or two scenarios. But anyway,
in principle she is entitled to take it back out. How that
plays out in the fact that it's limited to their original value,
that's not exactly clear. Let's take a look. We rule like רב
יהודה. Rav Yehuda. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava l'Rav
Nachman, so רבא Rava said to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, because he
said, רב נחמן Rav Nachman was the one who said we rule
like רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and רבא Rava is passing on that
tradition. So רבא Rava now said to
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, והתניא כוותיה דרבי אמי? v'hatanya k'vassa d'Rabbi Ami?
We just but we taught a ברייתא braita like רבי אמי. Rabbi
Ami. The ברייתא braita about the what do you call it, about
the שן ועין, shen v'ayin, which was not so persuasive as תוספות
Tosafos says. You know, even even רבי אמי, Rabbi Ami, even if
they're hers because he has all those rights, it could still be
that the same way they eat תרומה trumah by virtue of him,
the idea of of going free when of the שן ועין shen
v'ayin could be by virtue of him. So תוספות Tosafos doesn't understand
why that was a proof to רבי אמי, Rabbi Ami, but that's
what רבא Rava said, that whole story about the going out by
the eye and the tooth, that seems to be a proof to
רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. והתניא כוותיה דרבי אמי. v'hatanya k'vassa d'Rabbi Ami.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אע"ג דתניא כוותיה דרבי אמי מסתבר טעמא
דרב יהודה. af al gav d'tanya k'vassa d'Rabbi Ami mistabra ta'ama d'Rav
Yehuda. You know what, even though the ברייתא braita seems to go
like him, מסתבר טעמא דרב יהודה משום שבח בית אביה mistabra ta'ama
d'Rav Yehuda mishum shevach beis aviha because it because it because ultimately
this is stuff she got from her father's house, which is again
quite fascinating, right? It's not really much of a legal argument. Okay,
she got it from her father's house, fine. But what happens once
she brings it in? You know? And the there's a textual evidence
but we're sort of discarding it because there's a sense like she
should be entitled to it. All right, anyway, but actually the to
me the stronger ברייתא braita was was like רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
was that it is hers because that's all about his not being
allowed to sell it. Okay, now a story.
ההיא איתתא דאייתי ליה לגברי איצטלא דמילתא. Hahi itesa d'aysi leh l'gavrei
itztala d'milsa. There was a woman that brought in with her dowry
a very like a a cloak of fine wool. בכתובתה, B'kesuvashah, for
in her כתובה, kesuva, for her dowry. שכיב, Schiv, then the... died.
Okay, so now based on what we said, if we rule like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda she should be able to take it back
out. But שקלוה יתמי, shakluah yatmi, before she had a chance to
do anything, the orphans came and ופרסוה אמיתנא u-parsuha a-misna and they
spread it over the dead body and they wanted to use it
as a shroud. So and we know that something that is assigned
as a shroud and used as a shroud for a dead body
is אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, קניא מיסנא,
kanya misna, the dead body acquires it, meaning it now is considered
a shroud and she loses her rights to it. I mean she's
still entitled to the value from the estate for her dowry, but
she loses yes, but she loses any rights in this particular object.
So אמר ליה מנכי בריה דרב יוסף בריה דרבא לרב כהנא, Amar
leh Menchi breih de-Rav Yosef breih de-Rava le-Rav Kahana, so this מנכי
Menchi the grandson of רבא Rava said to רב כהנא, Rav Kahana,
דאמר רבא אמר רב נחמן הלכה כרבי יהודה, de-Amar Rava Amar Rav
Nachman Halacha ke-Rabbi Yehuda, don't we rule like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
And therefore it should have been hers. And if you take somebody
else's garment and you put it on a dead body, it doesn't
become a shroud. You can't change the status of something you don't
own. You can only do that with your own objects. So if
this is hers, the orphans weren't entitled to use it as a
shroud and it shouldn't change its status.
So אמר ליה, Amar leh, he said back to him, מי לא
מודה רבי יהודה דמחוסר גוביינא? mi lo modeh Rabbi Yehuda de-mechusar gubyanya?
Even though רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says she's entitled to take it
back, it still needs to be collected. Meaning, so this becomes a
fascinating
question. Is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying it's hers, the title remains
hers, or is she saying she has a right to retrieve it?
Technically the title is his, but she ultimately retains the right to
like, you know, to re-exercise her claim on it if he dies.
So it's a little bit sounding like the latter. Like it's not
like it's totally her title. She has a right to claim it,
but it requires to go ahead and to be claimed and to
be collected. And until that point, it's not yet hers or certainly
not under her control. Right? I mean all along it goes under
the husband's control. So even after the husband dies, it doesn't automatically
revert to her control. That needs to actually be delivered and collected.
So therefore, דכיון דמחוסר גוביינא ברשותיה קאי, de-kivun de-mechusar gubyanya bi-reshusei kai,
and since it requires being collected, it's still under the control of
the husband or the heirs. Okay, and therefore they're in a position
again—do they have title? Does she have title? Not exactly spelled out.
It might be she has title but no control. But anyway, since
they're the ones still in control, they are in a position to
use it for the dead body and then that'll take away her
rights. Why? Why? רבא—well Rava no, he still owes the money. She
still gets the money from the estate, she just loses the rights
in this object.
Because she didn't have any obligation to bury her husband and provide
תכריכין.
tachrichin. Yeah, that's a different subject. But yes, רבא לטעמיה דאמר רבא,
Rava le-taimeih de-Amar Rava, רבא Rava goes according to his reasoning because
רבא Rava said: הקדש חמץ ושחרור מוציאין מידי שיעבוד. Hekdesh chametz u-shichrur
motzi'in mi-yedei shibud.
That if you basically have a lien on my estate and I
go ahead and I sanctify—you have a lien on my plot of
land and I sanctify it. Okay actually no, that would be a
קדושת דמים kedushat damim example, this is only קדושת הגוף. kedushat ha-guf.
You have a lien on my cow and I make it into
a קרבן. korban. But it's only when you actually change its status,
not just that you transfer its ownership to הקדש. hekdesh. I make
the cow into a קרבן, korban, your lien disappears. Okay, that idea
of that I've made it into a קרבן korban changes its identity.
You're a non-Jew, you have a lien on my חמץ, chametz, it
becomes פסח, Pesach, חמץ chametz becomes אסור בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, your lien
disappears. That changes its identity. Okay, you have a lien on my
slave, I free my slave, my slave has now transformed his identity,
your lien disappears. So here too, she has a type of a
lien or a right on this cloak, but they basically put it
on the dead body, they made it אסור בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, that's
like the חמץ chametz the פסח Pesach case or like הקדש, hekdesh,
maybe even more like the חמץ chametz the פסח Pesach case. And
that completely therefore transfers its identity and therefore all of her, you
know, monetary rights, all of her, you know, have gone—basically are removed.
So that's why that worked. But the important conceptual point for us
immediately being that even if she is entitled to it, it doesn't
mean it automatically reverts to her control. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, says רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, top of ס"ז עמוד א', samech zayin amud aleph,
הכניסה לו שני כלים באלף זוז. hichnisah lo shenei kelim be-elef zuz.
So now we're going to get an interesting case, right, similar to
sort of what—some of the scenarios I was giving you. She brings
in two vessels worth a thousand dollars. ושבחו ועמדו על שני אלפים.
ve-shavchu ve-amdu al shenei alafim.
And now they're worth two thousand dollars. What does she retrieve? אחד
נוטלה בכתובתה. echad notalah bi-chtuvtasah. So one she gets back, right, because
she's entitled to get it back. ואחד נותנת דמים ונוטלה מפני שבח
בית אביה. ve-echad nosenet damim ve-notalah mipnei shevach beit aviha. And the
other one she actually is entitled to demand the other one back
and she just has to pay the increase in value. So there's
like a scenario I gave you, okay, which is that she actually
is entitled to get it all back and if it's worth more
she pays the difference. Now why? Maybe she should only be entitled
to one because she's only has rights up to the value of
what she brought in. So again the reason is מפני שבח בית
אביה. mipnei shevach beit aviha. Now again a special consideration that we
give her, this is the stuff that she brought in from her
father's house. Again, even if technically she didn't bring it in from
her father's house, let's say she married after she had earned money
for herself, but it doesn't matter conceptually. actually stuff she brought in
from her father's house, therefore we're going to you know sort of
have the law favor her in these types of things and give
her the right to retrieve both of them even though now it's
worth double and pay the difference. Okay? So the Gemara says מאי
קא משמע לן, mai kamashma lan, what are you teaching me? שבח
בית אביה דידה הוי, shevach beis aviha ddidah havei, so that she's
entitled to what she brought in. הא אמר רב יהודה חדא זימנא,
ha amar Rav Yehuda chada zimna, didn't we already say that? No.
מהו דתימא הני מילי היכא דמטא למשקל בכתובתה, mahu d'teima hani mili
heicha d'mata limshkal b'khsubasah, maybe that's only up to the original value
of the ketubah, אבל מיתן דמי ומישקל לא, aval mitan damei umishkal
lo, but to actually be able to pay the difference in value
and take stuff that went beyond the original value in order to
retrieve it, maybe she wouldn't have that right. קא משמע לן kamashma
lan that she does. Okay? So the Gemara is very clear that
she has the right to retrieve everything she brought in, if it's
worth more she pays the difference. Let's and the flip would also
be true now, if it's worth less, she retrieves everything and the
husband's estate has to pay the difference. Okay? So that exactly is
so that's so all of this is done, you know, and again
it's interesting the way sort of the the desire to give her
back what she you know what she brought in drives, you know,
the way in which we determine her rights in this situation.
You know what they actually did today?
What we do today? I don't know. You have to first go
to Eretz Yisrael where they done these cases and then there was
a lot of תקנות takanos to protect the woman's interests even more
in the time of the גאונים geonim and so on. All right,
next משנה. mishna. בת ישראל שנישאת לכהן ומת והניחה מעוברת. bas Yisrael
shenises l'kohein umeis vehinnicha meuberet. So that was what happens if as
a result of the marriage she became a חללה. chalalah. What impact
that has on her נכסי מלוג. nichsei milug. Okay? So that was
the focus was on נכסי מלוג nichsei milug which is interesting was
her property although then we got into an interesting discussion of נכסי
צאן ברזל nichsei tzon barzel and to what degree she retains the
title on that as well. Now that's as a result of marriage
that it was an אסור assur marriage and she became a חללה.
chalalah. Now we turn to the question about not the marriage but
a child or a fetus and the role that the fetus plays
in terms of her status and in terms of the slave status.
So let's take a look. So you had a Jewish woman who
a non-kohenet who was married to a ישראל Yisrael Cohen ומת umeis
and then the Kohein dies והניחה מעוברת vehinnicha meuberet and leaves her
pregnant. Now when a Kohein dies and if again what we said
before is if he leaves behind a child through this woman, the
woman continues to eat תרומה. terumah. But here he did not leave
behind a born child, he left behind an unborn child, he left
behind a pregnant wife. What's the story? לא יאכלו, lo yokhlu, so
she the Gemara doesn't talk about the story with her, I'll just
tell you the story is she doesn't eat, she doesn't eat until
the child is born, okay? She doesn't eat by virtue of an
unborn child. But what's the story about the slaves? Okay? So לא
יאכלו עבדיה בתרומה, lo yokhlu avadeha b'terumah, the slaves cannot eat terumah
מפני חלקו של עובר mipnei chelko shel ubar because of the portion
of the ubar. Now עבדיה avadeha is a little funny because the
way it really means his slaves, okay? He's got slaves. Now he
leaves behind slaves and let's say he leaves behind sons, so the
sons inherit the slaves, so do the slaves continue to eat terumah
after he dies? Sure, because they're now owned by the sons and
they eat by virtue of the sons. But one of the part
owners of the slaves is this unborn fetus, okay? Because assuming that
he would be a son, we don't know, but if he were
a son he would be one of the unborn he would be
an unborn owner of the slave, a partial owner of the slave.
So because he has a partial ownership in the slave and he's
not yet born, so he's not yet in a position where he's
entitled to eat תרומה terumah and to have others eat on behalf
of him, none of the slaves can eat תרומה terumah because they
are part, ten percent of them is not entitled to eat תרומה.
terumah. The ten percent that's owned by the unborn son is not
entitled to eat תרומה terumah and the ninety percent that's owned by
the other let's say nine brothers or whatever is entitled, but that
part of me that's owned by the unborn son, he's not yet
entitled to eat, I cannot eat תרומה terumah by virtue of him
but I'm owned partly by him, so therefore the slaves cannot eat
תרומה. terumah. Yes?
I was going to ask a question. Okay. Does it challenge her?
Yes, yes, yes, that's the opinion of this משנה. mishna. The Gemara
well there's a lot of assumptions there. Okay. So let's take a
look. לא יאכלו עבדיה בתרומה מפני חלקו של עובר lo yokhlu avadeha
b'terumah mipnei chelko shel ubar because of the portion of the ubar
שהעובר פוסל ואינו מאכיל. sheha'ubar poseil v'eino ma'akhil.
The ubar invalidates and does not feed. So invalidates means he invalidates
the existing slaves from eating, he creates problems. And also he does
not help anybody, he doesn't, meaning his mother can't eat by virtue
of him either, okay? So פוסל ואינו מאכיל. poseil v'eino ma'akhil. So
he's the worst of both worlds,
right?
If he was completely
seen as yet not existing yet, then the slaves would eat. If
he was completely seen as born, his mother would eat. Right now
because he's in a middle state, it's enough that he has a
portion of the slaves but not enough that they can eat, and
he's not enough yet of a full person that because and his
mother can't eat by virtue of him. דברי רבי יוסי. divrei Rabbi
Yossi. That's what Rabbi Yossi says. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said
to Rabbi Yossi, מאחר שהעדת לנו על בת ישראל לכהן, me'acher she'eidasa
lanu al bas Yisrael l'kohein, if you're going to tell this is
true as to as to a ישראל Yisrael woman married to a
כהן, kohein, אף בת כהן לכהן. af bas kohein l'kohein. So the
same logic should be even if she was a daughter of a
כהן kohein married to a... So the עובר ubar still has a
portion and the slaves can't eat on account of the עובר. ubar.
Why does it matter if the mother's a כהן Kohen or בת
כהן Bat Kohen or the mother's a בת ישראל? Bat Yisrael? So
and אבא גולגול Aba Gulgul ומת ויש לו בן בבת ישראל יאכלו
עבדיו בתרומה מפני חלקו של עובר. u'meis v'yesh lo ben b'bat Yisrael
yokhalu avadav b'trumah mipnei chelko shel ubar.
And we don't know what his response is.
Is he challenging
them or saying he agreed with them? Well, it's not clear whether
they disagree with him or not, but they're just saying according to
your logic there should not be a difference between whether the mother
is ישראל Yisrael or a כהן. Kohen.
Could be, I mean, it
just sounds like what do you hear? No, well we'll see in
the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look. איבעיא להו. I'bai'lehu. So now
we're going to try to figure out what his reason is. טעמא
דרבי יוסי משום דקסבר עובר במעי זרה זר הוא? Ta'ama d'Rabbi Yosi
mishum d'kasavar ubar b'mei zara zar hu?
Maybe and this is going to point to why what רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi might really have been holding. Maybe the reason is not
that the עובר ubar has a portion of the slaves and the
slaves can't eat yet because he's not born. They can't eat through
him. Maybe the reason is that until he's born he's not yet
a כהן. Kohen. So he has a portion of the slaves, but
the reason they can't eat by virtue of him is not that
you have to be alive and entitled to eat and therefore the
slaves can eat because you can eat. The reason they can't eat
is because he's because he's a non-כהן Kohen who owns them. ומעי
אמו? U'mei imo? Right, yeah, exactly. So and while he's still in
his mother and before he gets his independent identity and since his
mother is a non-כהן, Kohen, he's a non-כהן. Kohen. And therefore if
he's a part owner, they can't eat because part of them is
owned by a non-כהן. Kohen. Okay, is that why? או דלמא ילוד
מאכיל שאין ילוד אינו מאכיל? O dilma yalud ma'akhil she'eino yalud eino
ma'akhil? It has nothing to do with him not being a כהן.
Kohen. He's a כהן. Kohen. But nevertheless the principle is that slaves
can only eat by virtue of somebody who's born, not by virtue
of somebody who's unborn. So the obvious נפקא מינה nafka mina of
those two cases is: what if his mother is a בת כהן?
Bat Kohen? Right? That's the difference. Is it all because his mother's
a ישראלית Yisraelit and that makes him a זר? zar? Or is
it because he's unborn? So that exactly seems to be what might
be going on in the משנה. Mishnah. Let's take a look. למאי
נפקא מינה לעובר במעי כהנת. מאי? L'mai nafka mina l'ubar b'mei Kohenet.
Mai? So his mother's a כהנת, Kohenet, a בת כהן. Bat Kohen.
What's the story? So אמר רבה: Amar Rabba: היינו טעמא דרבי יוסי
כדקסבר עובר במעי זרה זר הוא. Hainu ta'ama d'Rabbi Yosi k'd'kasavar ubar
b'mei zara zar hu. Yeah, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi thinks it's because
his mother's a non-כהן Kohen and therefore the עובר ubar is a
זר. zar. רב יוסף אמר: Rav Yosef amar: ילוד מאכיל שאין ילוד
אינו מאכיל. Yalud ma'akhil she'eino yalud eino ma'akhil. No, it's because he's
unborn. It's not because his mother's a non-כהן. Kohen. So, מתיב, Meiteiv,
I'm sorry, שאין ילוד אינו מאכיל. she'eino yalud eino ma'akhil. מתיב, Meiteiv,
ask on this: אמרו לו לרבי יוסי מאחר שהערת לנו על בת
ישראל לכהן, Amru lo l'Rabbi Yosi me'achar she'he'arta lanu al Bat Yisrael
l'Kohen, once you told us this is true if his mother is
a בת ישראל, Bat Yisrael, בת כהן לכהן מהו? Bat Kohen l'Kohen
mahu? This is a ברייתא braita that elaborates on the משנה. Mishnah.
What would you say the הלכה halakha is if his mother was
a
בת כהן? Bat Kohen? אמר להם: Amar lahem: זו שמעתי וזו לא
שמעתי. Zo shamati v'zo lo shamati. No, I have a tradition about
when the mother's a ישראלית, Yisraelit, that the slaves can't eat. When
the mother's a בת כהן, Bat Kohen, that I don't know. That
I don't have a tradition, which presumably means that they could eat.
So what would be the reason for the difference? אי אמרת בשלמא
עובר במעי זרה זר הוא, Ei amrat bishlama ubar b'mei zara zar
hu, היינו דקאמר ליה זו שמעתי וזו לא שמעתי. ha'inu d'ka'amar lei
zo shamati v'zo lo shamati. If it's for the reason that he's
a זר, zar, so we understand why he only says this when
his mother's a ישראלית. Yisraelit. That's exactly the reason. אי אמרת ילוד
מאכיל שאין ילוד אינו מאכיל, Ei amrat yalud ma'akhil she'eino yalud eino
ma'akhil, מאי זו שמעתי וזו לא שמעתי? mai zo shamati v'zo lo
shamati? Why would he not say, well of course you're right, it
is the same
הלכה? halakha? It's the exact same issue if it's about being born
or unborn. תא שמע. Ta shema. The גמרא Gemara says, okay, that's
a good question. We don't know. Which basically means that the רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi never out and out says it's a different הלכה
halakha if the mother's a כהנת. Kohenet. Clearly the Rabbis said, based
on your logic it should be the same הלכה. halakha. So the
Rabbis clearly understood רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi that it's about שאין ילוד
אינו מאכיל, she'eino yalud eino ma'akhil, right? That as long as you're
not born, your slaves can't eat on your behalf. Did רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi himself agree that that was the reason and just didn't
sort of draw the necessary conclusion? Or was רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
really of a different position? That it was because his mother was
a ישראלית Yisraelit and therefore the fetus was considered a זר. zar.
So we don't exactly know how to get to the bottom of
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, but it's clear that that is the issue
going on below the surface. Okay, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: זו דברי רבי יוסי. Zu divrei Rabbi Yosi.
This is the position of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. אבל חכמים אומרים,
Aval Chakhamim omrim, but the Sages say, because this is the point
in the משנה, Mishnah, it's not clear the Sages just disagree. They
just want to say the logical conclusion of what you said is
that it would apply even if the mother's a כהן. Kohen. But
now we're going to have a real disagreement. This was the position
of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, but the Sages say: יש לו בנים
אוכלין משום בנים. Yesh lo banim okhlin mishum banim.
If there are already
children, that here is the mother who is
pregnant. Are there other children or not to this כהן? Kohen? If
there are other children, they can eat by virtue of the other
children. The presence of a fetus, of an unborn fetus, doesn't make
it worse. אוכלין משום בנים. Okhlin mishum banim. אין לו בנים, Ein
lo banim, let's say there are no children, אוכלין משום אחים. okhlin
mishum achim.
Then who, before a fetus is born, the Sages would be saying,
not only like there are two assumptions of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi.
Number one is an unborn fetus already takes title of his inheritance,
right? Understand that that's assumption number one. And assumption number two is...
The slaves can't eat by virtue of him because he's unborn. So
the חכמים Chachamim here disagree with assumption number one. He doesn't take
title of his inheritance, so he's completely out of the picture. So
if there are brothers, they eat by virtue of the brothers. I
mean if there's sons, they eat by virtue of the sons. If
there's no sons, it's not like well the עובר Ubar is now
the heir. Right? Remember whether a boy or a girl, if there's
no other children, once this fetus is born he will be the
heir. But says the חכמים, Chachamim, until he's born we consider the
brothers now, the other relatives the heirs. Right? They basically say until
this fetus is born he is not considered he has no title
to the estate.
So the slaves won't eat.
Well that's an interesting question. Can they go ahead and waste the
money knowing that this guy will be born? I don't know the
answer to that. But their basic point is they even before you
get to assumption two, can an unborn fetus have somebody eat on
his behalf? They say we disagree with assumption number one. Before he's
born he has no title to the estate. Okay. And therefore the
slaves eat based on whoever is whoever does have a title for
the time being.
So wait doesn't the woman actually own that property?
No. Why does she own the property? What the slaves?
Yeah so let's assume that's a good question. Let's assume we'll later
be talking about let's assume we're talking about נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei
tzon barzel before she retrieves them. Okay. Or let's say we're just
talking about the husband's slaves that he has independently of her. Okay.
I was just thinking about the ones she brought.
I know I know and the משנה Mishna was confusing because it
said עבדיה. avadeha. So it is a little confusing about that but
let's try to bracket that. Okay. So חכמים אומרים יש לו בנים
אוכלים משום בנים אין לו בנים אוכלים משום אחים אין לו אחים
אוכלים משום משפחה כולה. Chachamim omrim yesh lo banim ochlim mishum banim
ein lo banim ochlim mishum achim ein lo achim ochlim mishum mishpacha
kula.
Meaning there's somebody around that's related to this כהן Kohen that's alive.
Okay. That person is the heir until the fetus is born and
for that because of that person the slaves can eat תרומה. Terumah.
Okay is that clear? So they basically reject the first principle and
they say until this עובר Ubar fetus is born he's not even
in the picture.
He is not מאכיל.
ma'achil. Right. Okay. So that's the חכמים Chachamim disagree. That's disagreeing with
principle number one. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says okay. So זו
ולא סבירא ליה. zu velo sevira leh.
Now when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says
this is the words of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose it sounds like
he's saying like okay that's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose's position but we
don't hold of it because there's this other position of the sages
that completely rejects it. So the גמרא Gemara says is that really
true that שמואל Shmuel doesn't hold of רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose? זו
ולא סבירא ליה? zu velo sevira leh? ואמר ליה שמואל לרב חנא
בגדתאה. ve'amar leh Shmuel leRav Chana Bagdata. Didn't שמואל Shmuel say to
רב חנא בגדתאה? Rav Chana Bagdata? Now what does בגדתאה Bagdata mean?
So if you look at רש"י Rashi it's like two lines below
the ב"ח. Bach. רש"י Rashi says בגדתאה. Bagdata. First he says בעל
אגדה ba'al agadah or so he was a somebody who liked sort
of teaching אגדה. agadah. לשון אחר שם מקום שבבבל ששמו בגדד. lashon
acher shem makom shebeBavel sheshmo Baghdad.
So anyway which is probably the simpler פשט. pshat. Okay. So שמואל
Shmuel said to רב Rav to where were we? So is it
really true that שמואל Shmuel rejects רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and says
that the fetus has no rights before he's born no rights in
the estate? ואמר ליה שמואל לרב חנא בגדתאה ve'amar leh Shmuel leRav
Chana Bagdata פוק אייתי לי בי עשרה puk aiti li be asara
go get me ten people ואימא לך באנפייהו ve'eima lach be'anpaihu I
will tell you in their presence המזכה לעובר קנה hamizakeh le'ubar kanah
that if somebody transfers title to a fetus the fetus takes possession.
So get me ten people I want to make a public declaration.
So you see שמואל Shmuel feels that you can transfer title to
a fetus. If you can transfer title to a fetus presumably a
fetus also inherits while he is still a fetus. So how do
you do that? Whatever דעת אחרת מקנה אותו. da'at acheret makneh oto.
You can be זוכה zocher for somebody. Okay. So therefore so why
is שמואל Shmuel saying oh this is what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
holds? It sounds like you don't agree. But you certainly agree to
principle number one. You agree that a fetus is entitled to a
portion of the estate. So what do you mean oh this is
what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose said? So the גמרא Gemara says fine
אלא זו וסבירא ליה. ela zu usvira leh. זו Zu doesn't mean
he's dismissing it. This is what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says and
this is how we hold. You should be aware there's the חכמים
Chachamim that disagree. חכמים Chachamim say the fetus isn't doesn't get a
portion of the estate. I happen to agree with רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose and I say that a fetus does get a portion of
the estate. Okay. That was only by the way only assumption number
one of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. So מאי קמשמע לן דפליגי עליה
דרבנן דרבי יוסי? mai kamashma lan depligi alei derabanan deRabbi Yose? And
he's just telling you look I'm not saying we don't rule like
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose but you should be aware that there is
another opinion out there. There's a rabbis that disagree and say the
fetus doesn't have a portion. Okay. ומי פליגי? umi paligi? Do the
rabbis really argue? So the word מתיב metiv is taken out. It
says והא אמר רבי זכאי veha amar Rabbi Zakai זו עדות העיד
רבי יוסי מפי שמעיה ואבטליון. zu edut he'id Rabbi Yose mipi Shemaya
ve'Avtalyon. This testimony that the because of the fetus the slaves don't
eat רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose gave in the presence of שמעיה ואבטליון
Shemaya ve'Avtalyon והודו לו vehodu lo and they conceded to him. So
if he testified to them and they agreed to him it sounds
like there's a consensus opinion that he's right. So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר רב אשי amar Rav Ashi מי קתני דקיבלו? mi katani
dekiblu? It doesn't say that they accepted the position. והודו לו קתני.
vehodu lo katani. It says that they agreed. So what's the difference
between agreed and accepted? דמסתבר טעמיה. demistaba ta'ameh. They said yeah that
actually makes a lot of sense. Okay but it doesn't mean they
actually chose to פסקן pasken like it. All right, so now we
have said that it's interesting, right? In the משנה, Mishna, you just
have the חכמים Chakhamim asking the rhetorical question, you don't have it
clear that anybody disagrees. The גמרא Gemara does present the position of
the חכמים Chakhamim that disagree and disagree with assumption number one, say
the fetus has no portion in the estate until he's born, but
that even שמואל Shmuel who presents that position of the חכמים Chakhamim
himself himself sides with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and says the fetus
does have a position a portion in the estate. Yes.
Two chronologically should שמעיה Shemaya and אבטליון Avtalyon were generations before רבי
יוסי?
Rabbi
Yosi?
I was trying to figure that out too.
And בגדאד Bagdad was founded in the eighth century by the Arabs.
Okay so then פגדתא Pagdata must be בגדאד, Bagdad, so thank you
for that. Okay.
All right. That's good to know. The רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi I
was wondering also in terms of the שמעיה ואבטליון. Shemaya veAvtalyon. I
don't know, maybe there's a different רבי
יוסי.
Rabbi Yosi.
He testified in the pres- oh, hey oh you're right I mis-
I mistranslated it. Thank you. I- I- thank you thank you I
completely mistranslated it. He didn't testify in front of שמעיה ואבטליון. Shemaya
veAvtalyon. He testified it in the name of שמעיה ואבטליון. Shemaya veAvtalyon.
Thank you, Michael. I- I mistranslated. That was a good catch. Okay.
So he gave this teaching over in the name of שמעיה ואבטליון
Shemaya veAvtalyon and they, I guess the sages, admitted conceded to him,
or they said that it was made a lot of sense, but
they didn't decide to פסקן pasken like it. Right right, he- it
was a tradition in their name. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. הניח
בנים heniah banim אלו ואלו אוכלין. elu veelu okhlin.
Let's say she leaves over-
he- what? She's not pregnant. Okay.
Well right we're not up to her being pregnant. Right. So the-
so now we're going to give all the scenarios. כהן Kohen dies
and there are sons. Okay, and there are no- forget anybody being
pregnant.
אלו ואלו elu veelu these and they meaning whether it's נכסי מלוג,
nikhsei melog, whether it's נכסי צאן ברזל nikhsei tzon barzel they can
eat. Why? נכסי צאן ברזל nikhsei tzon barzel can eat because they're
owned by until she collects them they're owned by the sons. They're
part of the estate. The נכסי מלוג nikhsei melog can eat. Who
owns the נכסי מלוג? nikhsei melog? She does. Why can they eat?
Because if there are sons left from the marriage, she can still
eat, right? Once there are sons, even after he dies, if there
are children that are still left that have resulted from the marriage
that are alive, she eats on their behalf, she eats through them.
So if there are children, both his slaves eat and her slaves
eat because everybody is eating by the account of the children. Okay.
אלו ואלו אוכלין. elu veelu okhlin. הניח מעוברת heniah meuberet let's say
she- he left her pregnant so אלו ואלו אינן אוכלין. elu veelu
einan okhlin. That's the teaching of the משנה. Mishna. She can't eat
until the child is born. She doesn't eat on behalf of the
children and therefore her slaves don't eat and the- his slaves don't
eat because this עובר ubar creates still this difficulty that he's a
partial owner but he can't they can't eat on his account. אלו
ואלו אינן אוכלין. elu veelu einan okhlin. That's like רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yosi. הניח בנים והניח מעוברת. heniah banim veheniah meuberet. Now, now we
get in- mixed case. הניח בנים והניח מעוברת. heniah banim veheniah meuberet.
There are sons around and she's pregnant. So עבדי מלוג אוכלין avdei
melog okhlin כדרך שהיא אוכלת. kederekh shehi okhelet. So because there are
children around, she's entitled to eat, right? The fact that there are
any child that's around and born entitles her to eat and therefore
her slaves can eat. עבדי צאן ברזל לא יאכלו מפני חלקו של
עובר. avdei tzon barzel lo yokhlu mipnei helko shel ubar. But the
fetus's part ownership in his estate prevents his slaves from eating. So
עובר פוסל ואינו מאכיל. ubar posel veeino maakhil. The
עובר ubar invalidates the ones that he's a partial owner in. So
even though there are other children who are also heirs, his partial
ownership creates a problem. And he can't cause his mother to eat
or his mother's slave to eat, but the other sons, the born
children do allow his mother to eat. דברי רבי יוסי. divrei Rabbi
Yosi. That's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says. So that was just
a nice playing out of the משנה. Mishna. רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי
אומר. Rabbi Yishmael berabbi Yosi omer. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael his son
says משום אביו mishum aviv in the name of his father so
הבת מאכלת הבן אינו מאכיל. habat maakhelet haben eino maakhil. The daughter
can have the mother eat but not the son. Not clear all
what that means. The גמרא Gemara will unpack that. Okay. רבי שמעון
בן יוחי אומר. Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai omer. רבי שמעון בן יוחי
Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai says זכרים יאכלו כולן. zekharim yokhlu kullan. נקבות
לא יאכלו. nekeivot lo yokhlu. שמא ימצא עובר זה. shema yimatzei ubar
zeh. I think we have to end here. Okay, we will continue
this משנה Mishna and see the range of positions of these scenarios
tomorrow as we...